Finding Aid for Robert Cooley Angell Papers 1923-1971
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Robert Cooley Angell Papers 1923-1971
Angell, Robert Cooley, 1899-
1 oversize volumes
3.5 linear feet
Professor of sociology, University of Michigan; correspondence and other papers concerning Angell's work with UNESCO, American Sociological Society, and International Sociological Association; papers concerning published books and articles; unpublished manuscripts of writings.
85849 Aa 2
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The collection was the gift of Robert C. Angell (donor no. 485 ) and came to the library in 1972. Scattered materials came later from Professor Angell and members of his family.
The collection is open for research.
Robert C. Angell, sociologist, was born April 29, 1899, in Detroit, Michigan. He was educated at the University of Michigan receiving his Ph. D. degree in 1924. His thesis on the student mind was later published under the title The Campus. He was appointed instructor in 1922 and assistant professor of sociology in 1924. At the time sociology was still taught within the department of economics and Angell's teacher and mentor was his uncle Charles Horton Cooley. Sociology gained departmental status in 1930 and Angell became associate professor that same year. In 1935, he became full professor. He served as chairman of the department from 1940 to 1952 and was instrumental in bringing to the department such individuals as Theodore Newcomb and Ronald Freedman, as well as the groups that formed the Survey Research Center and the Research Center for Group Dynamics.
Outside the department, Angell championed the importance of undergraduate instruction and helped to form the honors college, which he chaired from 1957 to 1961. With Kenneth Boulding, he helped to found the Journal for Conflict Resolution in 1954 and the Center for Research on Conflict Resolution in 1959.
Within his profession, Angell edited the American Sociological Review from 1946 to 1948 and was elected president of the American Sociological Association in 1951. He served abroad as director of UNESCO's Social Science Department in Paris from 1949 to 1950 and headed a project on world tensions. Partly as result of this work, Angell was instrumental in founding the International Sociological Association. He also served as this organization's second president. From 1950 to 1956 Angell was member of the U.S. National Commission for UNESCO.
Angell retired from the university in 1969 but continued to teach for a number of years. He died May 12, 1984.
The Angell papers document the life and professional activities of a renowned sociologist and university teacher. The collection dates from 1923 to 1984 though the bulk of the papers fall within the period of the 1940s through the 1960s. The collection has been arranged into five series: Biographical information/autobiographical essays; Correspondence; Books, articles, and other writings; Organizational Affiliations; and Topical Files.
Subjects:
American Sociological Association.; Angell, Robert Cooley, 1899-1984; International Sociological Association.; Sociology.; UNESCO.; University of Michigan--Faculty.; University of Michigan. Dept. of Sociology.
Subjects - Visual Material:
Angell, Robert Cooley, 1899-1984
Contributors:
Angell, James Rowland, 1869-1949.; Boulding, Kenneth E. (Kenneth Ewart), 1910-1993; Cooley, Charles Horton, 1864-1929.; Day, Edmund Ezra, 1883-1951.; Douglas, William O. (William Orville), 1898-1980.; Ford, Edsel, 1893-1943.; Group for Academic Freedom.; Hoover, J. Edgar (John Edgar), 1895-1972.; Humphrey, Hubert H. (Hubert Horatio), 1911-1978.; Jacobs, Albert Charles, 1900-1976.; Little, Clarence C. (Clarence Cook), b. 1888.; Llewellyn, Karl N. (Karl Nickerson), 1893-1962.; Lyons, Eugene, 1898-1985; MacIver, Robert M. (Robert Morrison), 1882-1970.; McKenzie, Roderick Duncan, 1885-1940.; McLaughlin, Andrew Cunningham, 1861-1947.; Merton, Robert King, 1910-; Moody, Blair, 1902-1954.; Mumford, Lewis, 1895-1990.; Murphy, Frank, 1890-1949.; National Citizens' Commission (U.S.); Parsons, Talcott, 1902-1979; Piaget, Jean, 1896-1980; Roosevelt, Eleanor, 1884-1962.; Tobin, Richard L. (Richard Lardner), 1910-; Women's Organization for National Prohibition Reform.
Genre/Form:
Diaries.; Videotapes.
- Biographical information/autobiographical essays
  The Biographical information/autobiographical essays series is of most interest for the various inspective essays that Angell wrote about his life and career.
  - Vita and other biographical information (Box 1)
  - Autobiographical essays, 3 folders (Box 1)
  - Appointment notifications, etc (Box 1)
  - Videotape interview of RCA conducted by Nancy Tucker, 1976, U-matic; 20 min. (Box 1)
  - Scrapbook (Volume 1)
    (maintained by different members of the Angell family relating to their lives and activities, includes clippings, correspondence, and memorabilia)
  - Loose items from scrapbook (Box 1)
- Correspondence
  The Correspondence series dates from 1921 to 1979 and illuminates Angell's professional relations with University of Michigan colleagues and with other sociologists. A selective inventory of Angell correspondents has been prepared and is appended to this finding aid. Correspondents include Kenneth Boulding, Charles Horton Cooley, Clarence Cook Little, Robert M. MacIver, Robert K. Merton, and Lewis Mumford.
  - 1921-1979, 22 folders (Box 1)
- Books, articles, and other writings
  The Books, articles, and other writings series consists of correspondence and other materials pertaining to his writings. There are also copies of unpublished papers.
  - The Campus-correspondence and clippings, 1927-1928 (Box 1)
  - A study in undergraduate adjustment-Letter, 1929 (Box 2)
  - Introductory sociology-Correspondence, 1933-1946 (Box 2)
  - The family encounters the depression-Correspondence, 1931-1966 (Box 2)
  - The integration of American Society-Correspondence, 1940-1964 (Box 2)
  - A critical review of the development of the personal document method in sociology, 1920-1940-Correspondence, 1941-1947 (Box 2)
  - The moral integration of American cities-Correspondence, 1940-1967 (Box 2)
  - Free society and moral crisis-Correspondence, 1956-1960 (Box 2)
  - Social values and foreign policy attitudes of Soviet and American elites-Correspondence, 1959-1967 (Box 2)
  - Peace on the March
    - Book outlines 1962 (Box 2)
    - Research correspondence 1963-1967, 2 folders (Box 2)
    - Publisher's correspondence 1964-1971 (Box 2)
    - General correspondence 1968-1971 (Box 2)
  - Unpublished manuscripts
    - A Nazi primer for Americans (Box 2)
    - Moral choice in the Metropolis (Box 2)
    - The sociology of international relations (Box 2)
    - Educational essays (untitled) (Box 2)
  - Miscellaneous articles and addresses, 5 folders (Box 2)
  - WUOM radio broadcasts on topic of "Education for Unity," 1946-1947 (Box 2)
  - Outline of talks (Box 2)
- Organizational Affiliations
  Organizational Affiliations is the series of files accumulated by Angell in connection with his activities with various professional organizations. These organizations include the American Sociological Association, the International Sociological Association, and UNESCO.
  - UNESCO
    - Correspondence 1950-1952 (Box 2)
    - Correspondence 1953-1968 (Box 2)
    - Talks about the organization (Box 2)
    - American Sociological Association Committee on UNESCO (Box 2)
    - Newspaper controversy with Malcom Bingay 1950 (Box 2)
  - American Sociological Association
    - General 1950-1952 (Box 2)
    - General 1953-1969 (Box 2)
    - Committee on Professional Ethics 1963-1969 (Box 2)
    - Sociological Resources for the Social Studies Project 1962-1971 (Box 2)
  - International Sociological Association
    - General 1950-1953, 1 folders (Box 2)
    - General 1954-1959, 4 folders (Box 3)
    - American Organizing Committee 1960-1962 (Box 3)
    - VI World Congress of Sociology 1964-1967 (Box 3)
- Topical File
  Files on various topics or activities have been brought together in the Topical Files series. There are multiple folders in this series of Angell course syllabi, files on his participation in the sesquicentennial celebration of the University of Michigan in 1967, and material on different research projects. Of interest are Angell's diaries while serving in World War II. Missing from this series are those records from Angell's service on university committees. Angell noted that he transferred his papers to his successor when his service was completed.
  - Association for a World Language 1965 (Box 3)
  - Children's International Summer Villages, Inc. (Box 3)
  - Course Material
    - Sociology 452 (Box 3)
    - Sociology 505 (Box 3)
    - Sociology 205 (Box 3)
    - Sociology 363 (Box 3)
    - Sociology 151 (Box 3)
  - Cranbrook Academy of Art 1951, 1969 (Box 3)
  - Intercollegiate athletics, trend toward the professionalization of 1961-1965 (Box 3)
  - Key Reporter, 1957-1962 (Box 3)
    (RCA was writer of review notes on books in the field of sociology and social anthropology)
  - Military/classified research
    - Institute for Defense Analyses and military research 1962-1963 (Box 3)
    - Effort to outlaw classified research at the university 1966-1971 (Box 3)
  - Military service, World War II
    - Orders, etc (Box 3)
    - Diaries of activities, 3 volumes (Box 3)
  - Pennsylvania (University of), evaluation of sociology department 1955-1956 (Box 3)
  - President's Advisory Committee concerning means of reducing university's budget 1933 (Box 3)
  - Research material
    - Social Welfare Laws Project 1929 (Box 3)
    - Program of research on moral integration 1946 (Box 3)
    - Social Science Research Council-Summer Seminar 1951 (Box 3)
    - International sociological research (Box 3)
    - Transnational Experiences and Congressional Foreign Policy Attitudes 1966 (Box 3)
    - Miscellaneous research notes (Box 3)
  - Ruthven, Alexander G. (interview with Peter E. Van de Water regarding his administration) 1970 (Box 3)
  - Sesquicentennial Celebration of the University of Michigan
    - General 1966-1967, 2 folders (Box 4)
    - Committee on Major Ceremony IV 1964-1967, 3 folders (Box 4)
    - Miscellanea 1967 (Box 4)
  - Travels
    - European travel journal 1932 (Box 4)
    - European travel journal 1935 (Box 4)
    - Trip to Soviet Union 1959-1961 (Box 4)
  - UN University (proposed) 1962-1970 (Box 4)
Selective Index of Correspondents
Angell, James Rowland $$$$LIST00000
Boulding, Kenneth Eward, 1910- $$$$LIST00001
Cooley, Charles Horton, 1864-1929. $$$$LIST00002
Day, Edmund Ezra, 1883-1951. $$$$LIST00003
Douglas, William O. (William Orville), 1898- $$$$LIST00004
Ford, Edsel, 1893-1943. $$$$LIST00005
Group for Academic Freedom $$$$LIST00006
Hoover, J. Edgar (John Edgar), 1895-1972. $$$$LIST00007
Humphrey, Hubert H. (Hubert Horatio), 1911-1978. $$$$LIST00008
Jacobs, Albert Charles, 1900-1976. $$$$LIST00009
Little, Clarence C. (Clarence Cook), b. 1888. $$$$LIST00010
Llewellyn, Karl N. (Karl Nickerson), 1893-1962. $$$$LIST00011
Lyons, Eugene, 1898- $$$$LIST00012
MacIver, Robert M. (Robert Morrison), 1882-1970. $$$$LIST00013
McKenzie, Roderick Duncan, 1885-1940. $$$$LIST00014
McLaughlin, Andrew Cunningham, 1861-1947. $$$$LIST00015
Merton, Robert King, 1910- $$$$LIST00016
Moody, Blair, 1902-1954. $$$$LIST00017
Mumford, Lewis, 1895- $$$$LIST00018
Murphy, Frank, 1890-1949. $$$$LIST00019
National Citizens' Commission (U.S.) $$$$LIST00020
Parsons, Talcott, 1902- $$$$LIST00021
Piaget, Jean, 1896- $$$$LIST00022
Roosevelt, Eleanor, 1884-1962. $$$$LIST00023
Tobin, Richard L. (Richard Lardner), 1910- $$$$LIST00024
Women's Organization for National Prohibition Reform $$$$LIST00025